<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Project | Haochen's Blog</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tag/project/</link><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Project</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url><title>Project</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tag/project/</link></image><item><title>What Did I DO -- IB Extended Essay</title><link>http://localhost:1313/blog/ib_ee/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/ib_ee/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the high school course of International Baccalaureate (IB), students are required to write an Extended Essay (EE) as a compulsory part of the curriculum. It&amp;rsquo;s a 4000-words research paper. To obtain high grade, depth of undergraduate level knowledge is usually required. I obtain a grade of A, which is the highest grade in IB system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I won&amp;rsquo;t talk too much about the content since its depth no longer worth discussing in the view of my current level. I modelled the distribution of different random variables and trying to find the distribution of their sum, which allowed me to lead to the concept of characteristics functions, and then Fourier transform.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I choose to write my first blog about this essay because it really helped me to learn how to study.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="to-understand-this-try-understand-that">To Understand This, Try Understand That&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>At first, I had a naive idea that if I want to achieve something, I just need to learn the things that are directly related to it. To write an essay about Fourier transform, I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to know how Fourier Series is derived. After reading articles about only Fourier transform, I realized that I was still unable to write out clearly what&amp;rsquo;s going on. I went back to Fourier Series and became able to derive it by myself. Suddenly, I realized why Fourier transform extracts the &amp;ldquo;characteristics&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This experience directly led me to take mathematics in undergraduate. My final goal is something like &amp;ldquo;Machine Learning Researcher&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Quantitative Analyst&amp;rdquo; and so on, but I think I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t study a tool in three years. Instead, taking a deep dive into the fundamental of mathematics is more important. Becoming a &amp;ldquo;statistician&amp;rdquo; and then contribute to the field of machine learning is more likely to make actual progress.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="do-it-before-learning-it">Do it Before Learning it&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This is an extremely useful rule when doing code. Before writing my EE, I knew little about python and nothing about LaTeX. I felt all the books and videos I could find are extremely boring. Without reading and watching even one of them, I trid to do data scraping and draw data in Python. I tried to write my EE in LaTeX. Everytime I encountered a problem, I searched for the solution. The program for my essay was done in half a day and I even began to earn money by writing LaTeX for others after wrting the first draft of my essay.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>