<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Project | Haochen's Blog</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tag/project/</link><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Project</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url><title>Project</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tag/project/</link></image><item><title>My Work -- Year 1 Individual Research Project</title><link>http://localhost:1313/blog/point_process/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/point_process/</guid><description>&lt;p>All concepts mentioned in this blog are explained here:
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the last term of Year 1, each student in my class was required to complete an individual research project. It&amp;rsquo;s only a single page poster. I was allocated the topic of point process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After studying several types of point processes, such as Possion Process, Renewal Process and so on, I think I want to find some method which is more general and easy to use, and of course, allow me to extend the topic. So I chose Kernel Density Estimation (KDE) as my method to analyze the data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The whole project is easy to conclude.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Model the density distribution of KDE.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Explain the relationship between density and intensity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Obtain the point process and analyze the final result.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Funny thing is that I implemented the KDE by cuml, which is a library designed for GPU accelerated machine learning. During my Year 1, I was looking forward to doing some machine learning projects, but I felt that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a chance in a math department. After finish KDE on crime data, I realized that I had just finished a machine learning project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even though KDE doesn&amp;rsquo;t have some important abilities for famous machine learning algorithms, it does follows that basic definition of machine learning which is algrithm that can learn from data and improve from experience. The more data I have, the more kernels I can put on the estimation, and the estimation will be closer to real distribution. KDE seems to be a good regression model for probability distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This experience made me more believe in the idea that, machine learning is a branch of statistics. I have never seen articles, essays or books that define KDE as a machine learning algorithm, but it follows the definition.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My Word -- IB Extended Essay</title><link>http://localhost:1313/blog/ib_ee/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/ib_ee/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of the International Baccalaureate (IB) program, students are required to complete an Extended Essay (EE), a 4,000-word research paper. Achieving a high grade often requires knowledge at an undergraduate level. I earned an &amp;lsquo;A,&amp;rsquo; the highest grade awarded by the IB system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While I won’t delve deeply into the content—since its complexity no longer feels challenging given my current level—I focused on modeling the distribution of various random variables and explored how to determine the distribution of their sum. This journey led me to concepts like characteristic functions and Fourier transforms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I chose this essay for my first blog post because it played a key role in teaching me how to learn.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="to-understand-this-you-must-understand-that">To Understand This, You Must Understand That&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Initially, I believed that to achieve something, all I needed was to study the things directly related to my goal. For example, I thought that to write an essay on Fourier transforms, I didn’t need to understand Fourier series derivations. After reading material solely about Fourier transforms, I realized I still couldn’t clearly explain the concept. So, I revisited Fourier series and learned how to derive it on my own. Suddenly, why Fourier transforms extract &amp;ldquo;charcteristics&amp;rdquo; of functions became clear.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This realization significantly shaped my academic trajectory, ultimately leading me to pursue mathematics at the undergraduate level. While my long-term goals include becoming something like a &amp;ldquo;Machine Learning Researcher&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Quantitative Analyst,&amp;rdquo; I believe the most valuable approach isn&amp;rsquo;t to spend three years studying specific tools. Instead, a deep dive into the fundamentals of mathematics feels essential. By becoming a statistician and then contributing to the field of machine learning, I’m more likely to make meaningful progress.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="do-it-before-learning-it">Do It Before Learning It&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is an extremely useful rule when doing code. Before writing my EE, I knew little about python and nothing about LaTeX. I felt all the books and videos I could find are extremely boring. So instead of slogging through them, I jumped right into the practical work—I started with data scraping and visualization using Python, and began drafting my essay in LaTeX. Every time I encountered a problem, I searched for a solution on the spot and continued from there. The program for my essay was completed in half a day, and I even began earning money by writing LaTeX for others after finishing the first draft of my essay.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>